[Music]
so good morning welcome back to the
lecture today we will be dealing with
tangent vectors and it is indeed
one of the technical
key concepts in mechanics and
we will of course develop this based on
the best of what we have done so far
but the intuition is probably
familiar to all of you imagine you are
moving you have a curve on
a manifold on a
differentiable manifold and
the intuition behind the tangent
vector is probably that you are walking and
when at a certain point in time you
are somewhere you can for
each specific point in time the
tangent vector to this curve
look at or one would physically
also say
one would physically also say the
velocity vector and it is actually
quite a nice picture and one
could now think well okay we embed
this manifold in a higher
dimensional space so for example
this two-dimensional manifold
here would be embedded in three-dimensional
space and can then of course the
vectors standing away in three-dimensional space
understand wonderfully
one can actually do it that way
but we do it technically differently for
a technical reason but also for
a philosophical reason because imagine
we want with this
manifold to describe the entire universe
the entire spacetime even
then it would be funny to have to
embed the entire universe in something even larger
and suddenly be able to talk about
velocity vectors of curves
to be able to speak of
yes that would then lie outside of the
universe that is at least
philosophically not very nice
and one calls this in differential
geometry one would call this picture
an extrinsic definition or
an extrinsic picture of a
tangent vector and what we
want to do is an intrinsic
definition in which the
velocity does not refer the
definition of the velocity vector
does not refer to the surrounding
space and I claim that it is also the
much more natural concept if you take
the new exercise sheet there is
a small picture in the upper right and there
it says underneath vector counter
that is the speedy driver yes the
vector that is the driver and indeed
your earliest childhood memories of
speed are certainly those
in the car then you drive in the car and a
car has at a certain
point in time a certain speed
okay and indeed speed
or velocity vector is indeed
a concept that we understand intuitively
and not one that we feel
needs to be defined via an embedding
space so the intrinsic
as a child you experience as a child in the car
the speed please per year that
is already advanced please yes that
is not advanced enough
you look out the window or and there
you see the trees passing by and the like
the posts on the side of the road right
right
that means you look at your surroundings
and watch how everything flows
past you and you could of course
also instead of putting up some posts there
you could also somehow
look there is a mountain range and you
drive past this mountain range and you
notice it gets higher and then
lower again as you look up through the window
and then hear how it
gets lower or if you now for example drive through
areas with large
temperature fluctuations then you
notice or the temperature is hot
or no sense there it gets cold again
noticeably faster you drive so
faster it alternates
that means when you drive along a curve
with your car and you observe
a surrounding let us say the
function values in the surrounding
temperatures mountain heights or such
something that is there and
look how they change while you
drive
the faster they change the
faster you are driving for given mountains
and given temperature distribution right
and for trees and whatever else
and exactly that is the intrinsic
description there you do not need any
surrounding space you only need
on the manifold on which you
drive reference functions okay that is
the intuition the extrinsic picture
what I just indicated is the
intrinsic picture and now we make
all of this technical and first section
smooth functions
and smooth curves so and this is
first of all a reminder of the
last lecture
there we had taken something like a
smooth manifold and what was that
again a smooth manifold
that was in any case a set M
of points then you had a
topology so that you at all
manifold becomes a topological
but then we also chose an atlas
and in this case a C
infinity atlas then the
manifold is called smooth and you remember
the C infinity atlas only has
charts such that when you consider the chart
transition functions they are
as functions from R to the m into R
to the dm smooth arbitrarily often continuously
differentiable and this smooth
manifold allows the
definition of smooth functions and since
we will need them again shortly
I will repeat them again we had
said that a function on the
manifold should be called smooth
if yes and now we need the
atlas if for every chart x that you
take from this atlas yes what was
again the condition for smoothness
expressed in the chart nobody can
remember that I cannot either
I always draw myself a picture so how
is this we have a chart U that
lies in M
there I can certainly apply f
then it is however
restricted to that which does not hurt us at the moment
does not hurt
then I have here the chart mapping
x goes to x of U
but that is a subset of R to the
d yes well the only thing I can
reasonably write here is f
to x inverse yes exactly that was
namely the representation of the function on
the chart instead of in the world world okay
and we wanted to call this C infinity
call it smooth if
this here is smooth
down there we can decide that
so if for every such chart
the mapping f x inverse which goes from
x of subset of R to the d
to R is smooth as a function
from R to the d into R
and you can verify this with the simplest
analytical methods
you remember that was the definition
of smooth function what I
had not shown you last time
but had already pointed out
that it works exactly the same way is
the definition of smooth curve so
if you now take a curve gamma
which first on a parameter
domain entirely in the manifold
lands so here our yellow friend
then you can also call this curve smooth
call it
there is a new definition that was
only the recycled one is called smooth if well
we want to do this again quite similarly
to do
we want to take a chart again
of course from our fancy
C infinity atlas and well this
diagram so that you do not
confuse it later just think of it
and likewise if you want to understand
this situation now then think
about what it looks like now you
have here if you land in a chart here
then you have you can of course
not take the entire parameter domain
because maybe this set
that you select there
there the curve goes in and out and
in and out possibly there you can
of course only when you restrict the curve with
this goal you can
of course only take the preimage of the curve of
this under the curve so these are
exactly the parameters that lie
in there then you have here again
the chart mapping goes to x
of are subset of the hoped for there we feel
at home and here you can
now make the successive executions
make now however nothing is after